Finding Aid for the Michael and Susan Kahn Collection of Political Cartoons LSC.2419
UCLA Library Special Collections
- 5. International Art, Prints, Broadsides and Ephemera, 1690-2010; Series 5; 21.9 linear feet (13 boxes, 1 map folder)
  - Eloquence founded on chemical principles, 1787; 1 Etching. Ink on paper. Aquatint? Penciled writing on verso of print reads: OCLC Indiana, satirizing Richard Watson's opposition to the French Commercial Treaty. (Box 78, Folder 4, Item 6)
    James Sayers was an attorney who quit his profession to become a political caricaturist. This work satirizes Richard Watson, Bishop of Llandaff, and his opposition to the French Commercial Treaty (The Eden Agreement).
  - The Gradual Abolition of the Slave Trade or leaving of Sugar by Degrees, 1792 April 13; 1 Print. Ink on paper. (Box 78, Folder 4, Item 10)
    Isaac Cruikshank was a Scottish caricaturist and painter who worked mostly in London. His sons Isaac Robert and George also became noted artists.
  - The Caricatures Magazine or Hudibrastic Mirror by G.M. Woodward, Esq. Vol. III, 1821 [title page], 1 Etching. Hand-colored etching. Title page only. (Box 78, Folder 4, Item 4)
  - London Sketch Book cartoons by "Faustin", circa 1874; 4 Lithographs (Box 78, Folder 2)
    4 pages double-sided with color cartoons adhered on paper.
  - Portrait of Arthur Adams, circa 1925; 1 Drawing (Box 80, Folder 11)
    A well-dressed man is shown walking in profile. He wears a top hat and smokes a pipe. "Arthur Adams" is written nearby and "Low" is signed in lower right corner.
  - Figaro cartoons from the series' of "Men of the Times", "Men of the Period", "The Royal Family", "The Disraeli Administration Sketch Book of Celebrities" by Faustin, circa 1874; 17 Prints (Box 80, Folder 12)
    17 illustrations depicting numerous politicians, royal figures and other British notables of the time.
  - Figaro's London Sketch Book of Celebrities - Her Royal Highness the Duchess of Edinburgh, 1874 January 21; 1 Engraving (Box 80, Folder 12)
    Cartoon clipping depiction of Her Royal Highness the Duchess of Edinburgh (Maria of Russia) in a white wedding dress and veil.
  - The Death-Hug, 1937 June 23; 1 Print. Single sheet illustration removed from Punch magazine. (Box 80, Folder 13)
  - The Great Sheik, 1937 March 24; 1 Print. Single sheet illustration removed from Punch magazine. (Box 80, Folder 13)
  - Aus einem Tage-Buch 1914, 1914/1915, 1915, 42 prints in 7 folders. Set of color prints adhered to paper organized into seven grey folders. (Box 80, Folder 14-17)
  - Farmer G--e Studying the Wind & Weather, 1771; 1 Etching (Box 80, Folder 3)
  - [Untitled political cartoon. Signed T.B.? Possibly depicts Amerique, Columbia, George Washington or George III.], circa 1780; 1 Print (Box 80, Folder 4)
    Possibly depicts Amerique or Columbia. Seller's note indicates they believe it's a military figure, possibly George Washington or King George III.
  - John Bull visited with the Blessings of Peace. No. XX, 1802 January 20; 1 Print (Box 80, Folder 5)
  - Amusement for John Bull & his Cousin Paddy, or, the Gambols of the American Buffalo, in St. James's Street, 1783 May 1; 1 Engraving. Print adhered in matboard. (Box 80, Folder 6)
    A large buffalo, representing America, has created havoc on St. James Street. A woman peddler has fallen over and spilled her basket of fish and bread onto the street, and English ministers rush to grab the goods. Two fight among themselves. Each minister makes a statement. George III watches the entire scene from a window and smiles. A delightful English satirical print on the American war. Cresswell 857. (Source: seller's note, see file.)
  - Boring a Secret of St[at]e... a hasty sketch of yesterdays business, circa 1785 July; 1 Etching (Box 80, Folder 7)
    James Sayers was an attorney who quit his profession to become a political caricaturist. This etching directs his satire at Irish politics.
  - The Yankee Doodles Intrenchments near Boston 1776, 1 Engraving (Box 80, Folder 8)
    Behind a well-made trench, fronted with palisades, appear the heads of its defenders; words issue from their mouths in long labels. One man stands on the top of the trench, his cap is inscribed Death or Liberty, his coat and stockings are ragged, and he stands as if shivering with cold, his bayonetted musket tucked under his arm and pointing downwards; he says I swear its plaguy Cold Jonathan; I don't think They'll Attack us, Now You... [SOURCE: Catalogue of Political and Personal Satires, number 5329]. Man depicted at far right is American General Israel Putnam [SOURCE (in this collection): George Washington's War: In Caricature and Print, p. 166)
  - [Untitled, copy of work featuring an interior scene in a home, people gathered around a table], circa 2000; 1 Print (Box 80, Folder 8)
    Copy of an image, possibly a painting. Kippenheim 1860 is written in lower right corner of work. (Kippenheim is a city in Germany.) Interior scene in a home with people gathered around a table for a meeting, looking intent and dismayed while listening to a young man speak. People bring food to the table as cats play on the floor in the foreground.
  - Coming Thro' the Rye [along with] The Mourners, circa 1900 March 19; March 20 [March 29?]; 1 two-sided print. (Box 81, Folder 1)
  - On the Black List [ along with] What He Wants to Know, circa 1900 February 23; February 25; 1 two-sided print. (Box 81, Folder 1)
  - Time's Magic Mirror [along with] Platitudinarianism, circa 1900 February 13; February 17; 1 two-sided print. (Box 81, Folder 1)
  - No Flirtation Allowed [along with] The Idol That He Loves, circa 1900 November 10-11; 1 two-sided print. (Box 81, Folder 1)
  - Glued Down [along with] Reviving a Decayed Industry, circa 1900 November 3; November 5; 1 two-sided print. (Box 81, Folder 1)
  - The Birmingham Swans [along with] The Hand Across the Ocean, circa 1900 January 29; February 4; 1 two-sided print. (Box 81, Folder 1)
  - Rothschild. Franzosische Karikatur von C. Leandre. 1898., 1922; 1 Print (Box 81, Folder 2)
    Anti-semitic content. This image (or a very similar image) was published on the cover of Le Rire in an issue from 1898.
  - The Old Bugbear [along with] St. George and the Dragon (new version), circa 1900 February 26-27; 1 two-sided print. (Box 81, Folder 2)
  - The Candid Friend [along with] Bringing Him Home, circa 1900 March 2; March 9; 1 two-sided print. (Box 81, Folder 2)
  - Wie Amschel Rothschild durch die Welt kutschiert -- die Pleitegeier vorgespannt. Frankfurter Karikatur. Um 1840., 1922; 1 Print (Box 81, Folder 2)
    Anti-semitic content.
  - Titelseite einer Nummer des russischen antisemitischen Wochenblattes "Pluvium". 1907., 1922; 1 Print (Box 81, Folder 2)
    Anti-semitic content. Titelseite einer Nummer des russischen antisemitischen Wochenblattes "Pluvium". Includes text with unknown language.
  - Wahlt Christlichsozial. Deutsche Christen. Rettet-Osterreich!, 1922; 1 Print (Box 81, Folder 2)
  - The Fairy Godfather [along with] The Passive Parrot, circa 1900 January 13-14; 1 two-sided print. (Box 81, Folder 3)
  - An Exploratory Operation [along with] The Dyke Borer, circa 1900 July 10; July 15; 1 two-sided print. (Box 81, Folder 3)
  - When He Comes back [along with] The Poor Orchids, circa 1900 March 13; March 18; 1 two-sided print. (Box 81, Folder 3)
  - A Perspective Diagram [along with] A Spirited Policy, The Bottle Trick, circa 1900 September 28; October 1; 1 two-sided print. (Box 81, Folder 3)
  - Albert Hahn: Onder Zwart Regime 12 Karikatuur-teekeningen in kleuren, 1905 September; Set of 12 color prints, unbound in soft paper portfolio. (Box 81, Folder 4, Item 4)
  - Národopisná Výstava: Českoslovanská v Praze, 1895; 2 Prints. Staple bound, soft cover. Acidic. Separating at bindings. (Box 81, Folder 4, Item 2-3)
    2 soft bound paper booklets, each include text, prints and photographs. Národopisná Výstava: Českoslovanská v Praze (translates roughly to: ethnographic exhibition Czechoslovak in Prague).
  - The Rake's Progress (New Series) (After Hogarth), Reprinted from St. Stephen's Review., 1887-1888; 1 Lithograph. Oblong folio. Leather and cloth. Cover completely separated from binding. Back cover looks like it has termite damage with a hole all the way through. Does not affect illustrated pages of interior. 15 x 11 x .25 (Box 81, Folder 4)
    The St. Stephen's Review was a weekly political publication published in London from about 1883 to 1892. Tom Merry was the stage and pen name of British performer and cartoonist William Mecham.
    Includes 9 full color illustrations published in St. Stephen's Review between June-August 1884. Each illustration, except one, includes a full page narrative of the Rake's Progress story.
  - 70 Dessins de Cappiello, 1905; Set of 70 colored prints bound in soft paper portfolio. No. 0,668. Paper (soft) cover; staple binding? Staining to cover of portfolio. (Box 81, Folder 5)
    Cappiello was a caricaturist, painter and poster designer who was born in Italy and worked mainly in France.
  - Daumier: Politische Karikaturen, 1944; 1 Print (Box 81, Folder 5)
    Set of black and white prints and biography, loose in soft paper portfolio. Full title is Daumier Politische Karikaturen. Sechzehn Wiedergaben Nach Original-Lithographien. Biographie und Bilderlauterungen von János Erényi.
  - Polska Karykatura Polityczna, 1951; Approximately 70 black and white and color prints with booklet. Soft cardboard, paper box portfolio with flaps containing booklet and loose prints. Box is likely acidic. (Box 82, Folder 1)
  - El Ahuizote (semanario feroz): Tomo I, 1989 June; 1 Reprint. Hardbound presentation folder inside of an illustrated paper cover. (Box 82, Folder 3)
    El Ahuizote was a political satire magazine published in Mexico City, Mexico from about 1874-1876. The name "El Ahuizote" has been used for more than one Mexican periodical title.
    Contents include a hardbound presentation folder inside of an illustrated paper slip cover with a run of 1989 reprints of issues of El Ahuizote from February 5-July 31, 1874 plus an informational booklet.